<?xml version="1.0"?>
<page><![CDATA[
<h3>ENHANCED MARRIAGE CEREMONY</h3>
<p>Will you all please stand for the bride&rsquo;s entrance.</p>
<p>You may all be seated.</p>
<p>Introduction</p>
<p>Prynhawn / Bora da, ar ran _______________________ a minnau _______________________, ga i eich croesawu&rsquo;n gynnes iawn i _______________________ i ddathlu priodas _______________________ &acirc; _______________________.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>Good afternoon / morning, on behalf of _______________________ and myself _______________________, I would like to extend a warm welcome you all here to _______________________ to celebrate the marriage of _______________________ and _______________________.</p>
<p>The place in which you have now met has been duly sanctioned according to the law for the celebration of marriages. &nbsp;You are here to witness the joining in matrimony of _______________________ and _______________________.</p>
<p>If any person present knows of any lawful impediment to this marriage, then he or she should declare it now.</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>Purpose of Marriage</p>
<p>The purpose of marriage is that you will always love, care for, and support each other through all the joys and sorrows of life, and that love may be fulfilled in a relationship of permanent and loving commitment. &nbsp;</p>
<p>Option 1 (optional)</p>
<p>_______________________ and _______________________ wish to marry, for in each other&rsquo;s company they have found fulfilment and love. As a consequence of this love they have drawn closer to one another and now wish to offer to each other the security that comes from legally binding vows, sincerely made and faithfully kept. You are here to witness this occasion and to share the joy which is theirs.</p>
<p>AND / OR</p>
<p>Option 2</p>
<p>Marriage joins two people who trust the love that they have found. &nbsp;It is a partnership in which each can grow and be their true selves, whilst sharing in the development of the other. &nbsp;It is a statement to all those around them of what the two of them know &ndash; namely that they have found such love, friendship and support that they wish to share for the rest of their lives. &nbsp; This marriage ceremony provides the opportunity to bring friends and family together in one place, to impart this message of love and commitment, and for everyone here today to celebrate the happiness of the married couple.</p>
<p>AND / OR</p>
<p>Option 3</p>
<p>Marriage is a desire by two people to share themselves and their experiences with each other, and a willingness to accept each other for who they are. Marriage means making a commitment to developing co-operation, friendship and mutual respect. It calls for honesty, patience and, of course, humour. Marriage is where each partner cares for the other and supports them in all that they do.</p>
<p>It demands courage &ndash; the courage to be open, the courage to grow and change, and the courage to sort out together the tasks of everyday living. Marriage requires closeness and distance &ndash; the closeness of a couple growing together, and enough distance to allow each partner to be individual. A good partner in such a marriage will be loving, caring, and above all, a best friend.</p>
<p>It is in this spirit that _______________________ &nbsp;and _______________________ are now before us. In each other&rsquo;s company they have found happiness, fulfilment and love. They now wish to affirm their relationship with this marriage.</p>
<p>AND / OR</p>
<p>Option 4</p>
<p>A successful marriage is one where each partner discovers that it is better to give love than to receive it. To truly love another person is to wish that person to develop and flourish in his or her own terms.</p>
<p>In a long marriage there will be joy and laughter, but also sadness and sorrow, harmony and discord, as you strive to overcome adversity and fulfil your dreams.<br /><br />The key value of wedlock is that it allows for intimacy between a woman and a man, who can enjoy each other's company, share ideals and expectations, confess failures and admit defeats to each other, and yet realise in union the qualities of the good life.<br /><br />Your marriage can become a work of art in which both of you together give it line and form, colour and tone. You will be challenged every day to make your marriage work. If you do, it can become a thing of beauty, a joint creation of aesthetic splendour and enduring value.</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>Reading (optional)</p>
<p>Can I please ask _______________________ to come forward for a reading.</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>Definition of Marriage</p>
<p>Before you are joined in matrimony, I have to remind you of the solemn and binding character of the ceremony of marriage.</p>
<p>Marriage, according to the law of this country is the union of one man with one woman, voluntarily entered into for life to the exclusion of all others.</p>
<p>This is the legal definition: but marriage as we all know, is more than just a legal contract. A successful marriage is where two people, living together as husband and wife, also love and respect each other; - they have confidence in the trust that they have in one another, they are able to share in each other&rsquo;s joys and sorrows, they care and support each other, not only through the good times but also through the difficult times which inevitably visit every marriage on occasions. We hope and trust that all these things will be a reality for you both in your married life together.</p>
<p>The union you enter into has to be done voluntarily and I ask each of you, therefore, this question: &nbsp;</p>
<p>Do you _______________________ by your own choice, enter into the union of marriage with _______________________ &nbsp;? (answer by saying &ldquo;I do&rdquo;)</p>
<p>Do you _______________________ &nbsp;by your own choice, enter into the union of marriage with _______________________ &nbsp;? (answer by saying &ldquo;I do&rdquo;)</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>First Declaration</p>
<p>Now I am going to ask each of you in turn to declare that you know of no lawful reason why you may not be joined in matrimony to each other. &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p>
<p>Groom to Bride</p>
<p>_______________________ please repeat after me:</p>
<p>Option 1</p>
<p>I do solemnly declare // that I know of no legal reason // why I, _______________________, // may not be joined in matrimony to _______________________.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 2</p>
<p>I declare that // I know of no legal reason // why I _______________________ // may not be joined in matrimony to _______________________.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 3</p>
<p>By replying &lsquo;I am&rsquo; to the question &ldquo;Are you _______________________ free lawfully to marry _______________________?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Bride to Groom</p>
<p>_______________________ please repeat after me:</p>
<p>Option 1</p>
<p>I do solemnly declare // that I know of no legal reason // why I, _______________________, // may not be joined in matrimony to _______________________.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 2</p>
<p>I declare that // I know of no legal reason // why I _______________________ // may not be joined in matrimony to _______________________.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 3</p>
<p>By replying &lsquo;I am&rsquo; to the question &ldquo;Are you _______________________ free lawfully to marry _______________________?&rdquo;</p>
<p>_______________________ and _______________________ you have gathered about you those whom you love the most. &nbsp;You invited them here today to receive their encouragement and support, and to celebrate with you on this special day. So, I ask you now, in the presence of this company:</p>
<p>Groom to Bride</p>
<p>_______________________ will you take _______________________ to be your wife, and will you remain true to her for the rest of your life together?</p>
<p>Answer: I WILL.</p>
<p>Bride to Groom</p>
<p>&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;, will you take &hellip;&hellip;.&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip;&hellip; to be your husband, and will you remain true to him for the rest of your life together?</p>
<p>Answer: I WILL.</p>
<p>Presenting the Bride to the Groom</p>
<p>WHO GIVES THIS WOMAN TO BE MARRIED TO THIS MAN?</p>
<p>(Bride&rsquo;s father (or someone else from the family) to come forward and say, &ldquo;I DO&rdquo;, and take bride&rsquo;s hand and place it in groom&rsquo;s hand.)</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>Second Declaration</p>
<p>Now the moment has come for _______________________and _______________________to contract their marriage before you their witnesses. Will you all please stand.</p>
<p>Groom to Bride</p>
<p>_______________________ please repeat after me:</p>
<p>Option 1</p>
<p>Call upon these persons here present // to witness that I _______________________ // do take thee _______________________ // to be my lawful wedded wife.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 2</p>
<p>I _______________________ // take _______________________ // to be my wedded wife.</p>
<p>AND</p>
<p>Option 3</p>
<p>To live together in love and harmony, // to cherish and care for you // now and always.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 4</p>
<p>Knowing in my heart // that you will be, //</p>
<p>My constant friend //</p>
<p>My partner in life //</p>
<p>And my one true love. //</p>
<p>On this special day, //</p>
<p>I give to you //</p>
<p>In the presence of these witnesses//</p>
<p>My promise to stay by your side //</p>
<p>As your faithful husband //</p>
<p>In joy and in sorrow //</p>
<p>I promise to love you without reservation //</p>
<p>Honour and respect you, //</p>
<p>Laugh with you and cry with you, //</p>
<p>Grow with you in mind and in spirit, //</p>
<p>Always be open with you, //</p>
<p>And cherish you //</p>
<p>As long as we both shall live.</p>
<p>Bride to Groom</p>
<p>_______________________ please repeat after me:</p>
<p>Option 1</p>
<p>Call upon these persons here present // to witness that I _______________________ // do take thee _______________________ // to be my lawful wedded husband.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 2</p>
<p>I _______________________ // take _______________________ // to be my wedded husband.</p>
<p>AND</p>
<p>Option 3</p>
<p>To live together in love and harmony, // to cherish and care for you // now and always.</p>
<p>OR</p>
<p>Option 4</p>
<p>Knowing in my heart // that you will be, //</p>
<p>My constant friend //</p>
<p>My partner in life //</p>
<p>And my one true love. //</p>
<p>On this special day, //</p>
<p>I give to you //</p>
<p>In the presence of these witnesses//</p>
<p>My promise to stay by your side //</p>
<p>As your faithful wife //</p>
<p>In joy and in sorrow //</p>
<p>I promise to love you without reservation //</p>
<p>Honour and respect you, //</p>
<p>Laugh with you and cry with you, //</p>
<p>Grow with you in mind and in spirit, //</p>
<p>Always be open with you, //</p>
<p>And cherish you //</p>
<p>As long as we both shall live.</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>Rings</p>
<p>We now come to the giving of the wedding ring/s which is the outward sign of the traditional way of sealing the bond which you have made with one another.</p>
<p>A ring also represents, in a symbolic way, the love and affection you have for each other.</p>
<p>Throughout the world, rings are a sign of eternity, for the circles they have no beginning or ending. These rings are a sign of your love and promises which you share together as husband and wife.</p>
<p>Can I please ask _______________________ to come forward with the wedding rings.</p>
<p>Groom to Bride</p>
<p>_______________________ please take _______________________&rsquo;s &nbsp;ring and place it on her third finger on the left hand and repeat after me :</p>
<p>Option 1</p>
<p>I give you this ring as a symbol of my love.</p>
<p>Option 2</p>
<p>I give you this ring // as a symbol // of my enduring love and affection. &nbsp;// I promise // to share my life fully with you, // to cherish and tenderly care for you, // to honour and encourage you, // to respect you as an individual // and to be true to you // through good times and bad.</p>
<p>Option 3</p>
<p>I give you this ring // as a token of our marriage // and as a symbol of my love // and all that we share. &nbsp;// Please wear it // with a feeling of love and pride // now and always.</p>
<p>Option 4</p>
<p>I give you this ring // as a sign of our marriage // and as a lasting reminder // of the vows made between us today. &nbsp;// It is a pledge // that I will honour you // and share with you // all that I possess // and that we will be together // from today onwards // through all the changing scenes of life // be they good or ill // and I will love and care for you // until Life&rsquo;s end.</p>
<p>Bride to Groom&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>_______________________ please take _______________________&rsquo;s &nbsp;ring and place it on her third finger on the left hand and repeat after me :</p>
<p>Option 1</p>
<p>I give you this ring as a symbol of my love.</p>
<p>Option 2</p>
<p>I give you this ring // as a symbol // of my enduring love and affection. &nbsp;// I promise // to share my life fully with you, // to cherish and tenderly care for you, // to honour and encourage you, // to respect you as an individual // and to be true to you // through good times and bad.</p>
<p>Option 3</p>
<p>I give you this ring // as a token of our marriage // and as a symbol of my love // and all that we share. &nbsp;// Please wear it // with a feeling of love and pride // now and always.</p>
<p>Option 4</p>
<p>I give you this ring // as a sign of our marriage // and as a lasting reminder // of the vows made between us today. &nbsp;// It is a pledge // that I will honour you // and share with you // all that I possess // and that we will be together // from today onwards // through all the changing scenes of life // be they good or ill // and I will love and care for you // until Life&rsquo;s end.</p>
<p>You may all be seated.</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>Reading</p>
<p>Can I please ask _______________________ to come forward with a reading.</p>
<p>&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;&hearts;</p>
<p>Conclusion</p>
<p>_______________________ and _______________________ you have both made the declarations prescribed by law, and have made a solemn and binding contract with each other, in the presence of your witnesses, family and friends.</p>
<p>May this day form a milestone in your lives to look back upon with much love and happiness. &nbsp;May the feelings of love that you have for each other deepen and grow even stronger throughout the years to come.</p>
<p>It therefore, gives me great pleasure to announce that you are now husband and wife together.</p>
<p>Signing of the Register</p>
<p>Photographs</p>
<p>Mr &amp; Mrs&nbsp;_______________________ &nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p>
]]></page>
